Announcer: Please welcome swix, Sarah Guo, Elad Gil, and Chairman and Chief Executive Officer
Announcer: of Microsoft, Satya Nadella.
Sarah Guo: I'm so excited to be here.
Sarah Guo: Welcome to a crossover episode of No Priors and Latent Space with Satya Nadella.
Sarah Guo: Congratulations on an amazing Build.
Satya Nadella: No, thank you so much. And it's great to be with both of you.
Satya Nadella: I listen to both of you or both the podcasts all the time.
Satya Nadella: It's great to be on it.
Elad Gil: Thank you so much.
Sarah Guo: So, you've just talking about these amazing announcements from across the Microsoft estate
Sarah Guo: all morning for, I think, three hours.
Sarah Guo: What is the— what's the most important reflection or takeaway you have?
Satya Nadella: I'd say there are, perhaps, the— the biggest one for me is
Satya Nadella: let's sort of conceptualize this more as an ecosystem play as opposed to a single model or
Satya Nadella: even a single platform, right?
Satya Nadella: I mean, you know, whatever.
Satya Nadella: At least for me, having grown up at Microsoft, having seen, whatever, four major platform
Satya Nadella: shifts, I sort of fall into that, uh, camp where a platform is defined by fundamentally
Satya Nadella: its ability to create more value above the platform versus what's captured in the platform.
Satya Nadella: And so, if you view what's happening right now, I think this morning's keynote was how can
Satya Nadella: any company, whether it's an AI-native company or a traditional enterprise company, participate
Satya Nadella: as a first-class participant where they can point to AI they create, right?
Satya Nadella: It's not that they don't use other people's AI.
Satya Nadella: Of course, they will. But to me, what's the path?
Satya Nadella: What's the recipe? How do I do it?
Satya Nadella: What does the stack look like?
Satya Nadella: What does the tooling look like?
Satya Nadella: What is valuable? How do you do that?
Satya Nadella: That's it. That's sort of our job to do.
Elad Gil: Yeah.
Sarah Guo: Ecosystem strategy is very complicated, right?
Sarah Guo: Because you end up building certain components, partnering for certain components, supporting
Sarah Guo: them. You just announced this big suite of models.
Sarah Guo: Like, tell us a little bit about the, uh, training strategy for Microsoft.
Satya Nadella: Yeah. So, so the thing that we wanted to do with the MAI models was to build, and as Mustafa
Satya Nadella: talked about, first of all, a great lineage, right?
Satya Nadella: Starting with pre-training, uh, with very good data quality, uh, doing all the ablations,
Satya Nadella: making sure, because in— in some sense, it's becoming even harder to build a clean lineage
Satya Nadella: model, mostly because there's so much stuff out there, um, that you truly need to ablate out
Satya Nadella: to be able to have a fantastic pre-trained model.
Satya Nadella: In fact, that's one of the challenges of a lot of the open-weight models is they look great
Satya Nadella: on one benchmark or two, but they're not great on practice.
Satya Nadella: So, that's why, in fact, even in our Phis, Phis are like— are pretty gone really excited about
Satya Nadella: these MAI models because how the heck can a small 5B model hill climb?
Satya Nadella: Um, and it goes back a little bit to what I think is ultimately the key thing to do, which
Satya Nadella: is try to pursue finding that cognitive core.
Satya Nadella: Uh, so to me, starting with a clean lineage, then creating that ability for companies
Satya Nadella: to be able to use this, right, not just as a generalist, but to create their own specialist
Satya Nadella: by building this hill-climbing scaffold around it, right?
Satya Nadella: So, it's not just the model, but you have a hill-climbing scaffold around it.
Satya Nadella: Then, you will start building your RLE.
Satya Nadella: You will start collecting the traces.
Satya Nadella: Most importantly, you'll have private evals because we know all the evals out there are good,
Satya Nadella: interesting, but they're not really that critical at this point because they all can be maxed.
Satya Nadella: And so, the point is each company will have its own private eval.
Satya Nadella: And so, that end-to-end platform story around our models is sort of,
Satya Nadella: uh, what I think is interesting.
Satya Nadella: And then, the one other thing, Sarah, since you brought that up is, I do feel there's a new
Satya Nadella: frontier. Like, people talk about the frontier, and are you operating at the frontier?
Satya Nadella: Um, interestingly enough, if you add a little temporality to it, you can use, let's say, in—
Satya Nadella: in fact, the— the Lando Lakes demo we showed was pretty cool.
Satya Nadella: We used, whatever, GPT-4o, right?
Satya Nadella: Then, you collected a bunch of traces, and then you took a 5B reasoning model and achieved
Satya Nadella: higher. Um, so, that is another aspect of what it means to appear— I mean, operate at the
Satya Nadella: frontier.
Elad Gil: Yeah. I think, uh, I— first of all, I have to congratulate you on, on basically building a
Elad Gil: frontier AI lab inside of Microsoft in two years.
Elad Gil: Um, I'm wondering, you know, uh, you have all this AI strategy that you're rolling out.
Elad Gil: I'm wondering what do you know now that you wish you would tell yourself two years ago, or
Elad Gil: two to three years ago?
Elad Gil: Three years for the Jensen partnership, two years for, uh, MAI.
Satya Nadella: Yeah, I mean, I think the— the thing that I reflect quite a bit, right, which is sort of,
Satya Nadella: obviously, I got into all this when I got excited by the— the scaling laws paper and, you
Satya Nadella: know, when— when even the OpenAI partnership came about when those folks said, "Hey, we're
Satya Nadella: going to really throw a lot of compute at transformers."
Satya Nadella: Um, and they've helped, right?
Satya Nadella: The thing that I always look back and say, "Wow, these things, um, do have capability that
Satya Nadella: they're climbing up." We— I mean, this, you know, this crude way of saying it is intelligence
Satya Nadella: is log of compute kind of works.
Satya Nadella: Now, what I think we underestimated, perhaps, is the real-world complexity of
Satya Nadella: deploying these so that they actually deliver the value in the real world, right?
Satya Nadella: So, the outcomes as measured by any benchmark is interesting, important, but the true eval
Satya Nadella: is when people out there are able to do unique things that they only can value, and it's very
Satya Nadella: measurable. Right? That I wish we had sort of even like had more in our consciousness, right,
Satya Nadella: which is as an industry.
Satya Nadella: Because right now, I think
Satya Nadella: when people say, "Well, I don't want a token max," it's an artifact of us not having taught
Satya Nadella: ourselves as an industry that we are using tokens to create value every step of the way.
Satya Nadella: So, I think that's kind of what I wish we had gotten there, but I'm glad we are here.
swix: What are some of the use cases that you've seen that have created the most value for your
swix: customers? Because I know that people talk a lot about code, and I think it's pretty clear
swix: that that's something that's having very large-scale impact.
swix: Are there other areas that you find in common that your customers are really benefiting from?
Satya Nadella: Yeah, I think, to your point, obviously, coding is now got.
Satya Nadella: But it's interesting, by the way, to even talk about the coding, right, which is coding has
Satya Nadella: worked so well. I mean, it's kind of nuts to see what we launched is like, oh
Satya Nadella: my God, I have these 100 agent sessions.
Satya Nadella: The cognitive load it transfers back to me as a human is so excessive that now I need a new
Satya Nadella: UI. Uh, oh, by the way, I— like, the— the chat as the only artifact is also impossible.
Satya Nadella: So, that's why we need a canvas.
Satya Nadella: So, it's kind of interesting for all the things about where is software needed or where is
Satya Nadella: UI needed, uh, you kind of need that even for code, right, in a fully agentic world.
Satya Nadella: But that said, one of the things that we are starting to see, we started seeing with Copilot,
Satya Nadella: but even some of the work we showed with auto— um, um, autopilots, right, on what you see
Satya Nadella: with claws, is a good one.
Satya Nadella: Because if you sort of think about a lot of human capital is doing the glue work, right?
Satya Nadella: If you now can augment that with tokens/agents that are long-running, durable,
Satya Nadella: right, then your ability to scale even what is still judgment and glue work gets amplified
Satya Nadella: like coding does. Uh, so, you can— like, I'm positive that six months from now, we'll all
Satya Nadella: be saying, "Oh, wow, like, all through the night, there was a bunch of stuff that all these
Satya Nadella: autopilots that I have working on my behalf with my delegated authority, so to speak, right,
Satya Nadella: I can sort of give even my identity, did a bunch of work."
Satya Nadella: Then, of course, I'll need my new IDE to say, "What did you do?
Satya Nadella: Like, did I do this work?"
Satya Nadella: and so on. So, I think that that's where compressing of workflows, uh, completing of tasks,
Satya Nadella: uh, that's where I think a lot of the value gets created.
swix: I think you raise a really interesting point, which is there's the actual agent is doing the
swix: code, and then there's a harness around it.
swix: And that's the environment, that's the context, that's everything you're setting up as a developer
swix: around actually a coding agent.
swix: What is the harness for the enterprise?
swix: Is there an equivalent concept for broader productivity work, or how do you think about that
swix: concept sort of—
Satya Nadella: That's right. So, so, in some sense, you kind of want the harness to define the models, the—
Satya Nadella: the data, uh, and the tools, and so that you have a loop across those three.
Satya Nadella: And so, what we are trying to, first of all, make sure is each of our products that we build,
Satya Nadella: right, whether it's GitHub Copilot or the security copilot, the stuff we showed with M-Dash,
Satya Nadella: or even the discovery for science, it doesn't matter.
Satya Nadella: All of them are multi-model harnesses, um, with tools access, so that you can do this progressive,
Satya Nadella: uh, disclosure of tools even, so that they're token efficient.
Satya Nadella: Uh, and then, you're feeding it with very rich context.
Satya Nadella: Because that's the other hard lesson we've learned in the last two years is, oh my God, the
Satya Nadella: amount of work you need to do to prep the context layer, uh, such
Satya Nadella: that your plan can execute in the most efficient way is where the magic is.
Satya Nadella: So, we have, in our case, we have the GitHub harness, which essentially we're using across
Satya Nadella: all our products. It's available in Foundry, and we're open, like, you can use your Llama
Satya Nadella: harness, whatever, or you can use the, um, uh, you know, any open harness or any harness of
Satya Nadella: yours and train with your tools and multiple models and your context.
Satya Nadella: And so, that's the pitch.
Satya Nadella: Because right now, a lot of dialogue is, um, "Hey, if I train the harness plus tools and the
Satya Nadella: model together, you get evals."
Satya Nadella: And what we are proving out is, and the best example of that is what we did with M-Dash, right?
Satya Nadella: Because when it launched, uh, it found bugs or vulnerabilities that were not found by Mythos.
Satya Nadella: Uh, and so, there is existence proof, I would claim, that you can have a multi-model harness,
Satya Nadella: uh, that can, in fact, be more, uh, performant in the real world.
Sarah Guo: So, a premise behind the training at the independent frontier labs is really, you know, we're
Sarah Guo: going to have these models, and we'll have an API business, and we'll support enterprises
Sarah Guo: and startups, but a first-party product, be it productivity or code or search, drives the
Sarah Guo: majority of revenue. That's a different value equation than you're describing, I think, with
Sarah Guo: the Microsoft ecosystem.
Sarah Guo: Uh, if— if that's the case, tell me if it's the case, uh, because obviously you have first-party
Sarah Guo: products and you have enablement products.
Sarah Guo: Um, what is the role of the develop— like, what is going to be hard, and the set of skills,
Sarah Guo: and the value capture that developer has in that world?
Satya Nadella: Yeah. So, so, I think that there's always going to be the case that someone who is super successful
Satya Nadella: as a platform builder can also have first-party products.
Satya Nadella: It was true with Windows, it was true, uh, with, um, like, the SaaS side and the cloud side
Satya Nadella: as well with us and others and so on.
Satya Nadella: But the thing that is is it should not be a limiter to other people achieving that same success,
Satya Nadella: right? That, I think, is the core difference, which is the— the network effects this time
Satya Nadella: around around intelligence are such because they learn from data, and not really lots of
Satya Nadella: data. It's just the few samples that you have to see to understand what's novel about something.
Satya Nadella: So, that's why the game becomes how to protect.
Satya Nadella: So, that's why I'd say every company having private evals may be the biggest IP.
Satya Nadella: Right? I think about it, like, what's that private eval that you can then use even a frontier
Satya Nadella: model to hill climb on and not leak the traces, maybe one of the biggest drivers, uh, of IP.
Satya Nadella: Like, so, in other words, another acid test is, you have an eval, that's private.
Satya Nadella: You're using a given model A.
Satya Nadella: Can you switch it to model B and, you know, climb up?
Satya Nadella: If you can, then you're in control.
Satya Nadella: If you can't, you're not in control.
Satya Nadella: And that's where even the harness decision becomes super important, right?
Satya Nadella: So, therefore, having an open harness, letting all models come in, having your evals, your
Satya Nadella: context, your tools, help you hill climb, I think, is the skills that an AI-native startup
Satya Nadella: needs, a SaaS company needs, or every enterprise needs.
Elad Gil: Yeah, I think in a very real way, you are— Microsoft historically is an operating systems
Elad Gil: company, and then became a cloud company.
Elad Gil: Maybe like the third act is that you're a harness or evals company, whatever— whatever the—
Elad Gil: the sort of conglomerate of concepts that you want to put together.
Elad Gil: Um, and— and I think, like, enabling every company to have like frontier intelligence or what—
Elad Gil: what— I forget the— the exact term that you used, um, is the— is the mission, right?
Elad Gil: Like, that— that is— that is the platform promise that you build with us, you will get your
Elad Gil: intelligence, uh, for your data.
Satya Nadella: That's right. To me, that is the— like, if there was one tagline, uh, for this entire developer
Satya Nadella: conference is, can everybody operate at the frontier with their frontier intelligence?
Satya Nadella: Right? To me, that is so important because otherwise, I— I don't know how you achieve stable
Satya Nadella: equilibrium, right, which is, how do I then go and say, "Oh, my company is going to have a
Satya Nadella: terminal value because I now know how to continuously compound on top of what's a platform
Satya Nadella: that gets better," right?
Satya Nadella: So, when, like, Windows, obviously, came out, Adobe built, Autodesk built, um, or even like
Satya Nadella: take what Jensen said, "We built DX, and he built, you know, CUDA on top of it."
Satya Nadella: Um, right? I mean, I always say to Jensen, "God, I got the short end of that, right?
Satya Nadella: I wish (laughing) we had recognized it."
Satya Nadella: But nevertheless, but that— that idea that you can build a platform layer that someone else
Satya Nadella: can then extend out, um, and build their own intelligence layer in this case, I think, is
Satya Nadella: everything, right? Without it, why have a developer conference?
Satya Nadella: I can just come and have you all sort of just worship at the altar of one model.
Satya Nadella: But that's not a developer conference.
Elad Gil: Uh, backstage, we had a discussion about what is IP or what is the value in a company.
Elad Gil: It used to be the length of human experience at the company, and now it's this other thing,
Elad Gil: which is the evals, the, uh, experience in sort of applying agents to the company.
Elad Gil: Can you— I just want you to like flesh that out a little bit more because it's very insightful.
Satya Nadella: Yeah, it's a great way to frame it, right?
Satya Nadella: Because at the end of the day, every company is going to have both the human capital that
Satya Nadella: is still going to be super valuable, uh, because humans, uh, and their ability to find the
Satya Nadella: gaps that exist at all times is going to be the way we all will create value, right?
Satya Nadella: I mean, so, I'm definitely in the camp that this is going to be about expressing new forms
Satya Nadella: of human agency and ambition even as token capital goes up, right?
Satya Nadella: So, let's say a— any corporation has lots of tokens and a lot of human capital.
Satya Nadella: The question is, how do you compound the two?
Satya Nadella: So, if you have a— like, if you take in Teams, I have a bunch of agents doing work and a bunch
Satya Nadella: of humans doing work, and the traces between those, that is really important context of how
Satya Nadella: that enterprise is creating value.
Satya Nadella: Then, that goes back to train, not a generalist model, but to train the— train the company
Satya Nadella: veteran agent. Uh, right?
Satya Nadella: That is super valuable again, right, which is when a company goes and says, "It should, in
Satya Nadella: fact, go on to the balance sheet," is how I think about it, right?
Satya Nadella: That's so, in fact, there may be like human capital was never possible to go put on a balance
Satya Nadella: sheet, uh, because you didn't know how to capture the tacit knowledge, whereas now, I think
Satya Nadella: you can with the agents that have learned through the— through time, through all the traces.
Satya Nadella: Uh, so, that's what at least we think will happen.
Elad Gil: I think the SEC is going to have to have accounting standards for token, uh, expertise.
Sarah Guo: Uh, you're talking about the equilibrium state, um, and a stable equilibrium where companies
Sarah Guo: have this kind of compounding value and can see terminal value for themselves.
Sarah Guo: Another, uh, challenge to, you know, the considered equilibrium of, okay, there are applications
Sarah Guo: and workflows that are sort of common to a vertical or a horizontal, um, and this was like
Sarah Guo: the generation of SaaS companies, and, you know, Microsoft has lots of SaaS properties as
Sarah Guo: well. And then there are things that are very specific to every enterprise that they're differentiated
Sarah Guo: against. Um, I'm sure you have heard much and participated in much of the debate about the
Sarah Guo: end of software because all these workflows are— are cheap to generate now.
Sarah Guo: Um, do you think the equilibrium looks different between what agents get built in enterprises
Sarah Guo: versus in their vendors in the future?
Satya Nadella: Yeah, so, I think what's happening there is, see, we— we had a particular way we captured,
Satya Nadella: uh, I would say, workflow in apps, right?
Satya Nadella: Because we built a— a data model, right?
Satya Nadella: We schematized some part of some business process.
Satya Nadella: Mhm. We then built a bunch of business logic.
Satya Nadella: Yep. And then we put a bunch of UI on top of it, right?
Satya Nadella: So, that's kind of what every SaaS company—
Sarah Guo: And then a little configuration.
Satya Nadella: Like 20 years, that was—
Satya Nadella: Right, and— and that was it.
Satya Nadella: So, interestingly enough, now you kind of get to relitigate that vertical stacking, right?
Satya Nadella: So, I still think, for example, that data model that you built underneath every SaaS application
Satya Nadella: is super good, right? It— like, why reinvent it?
Satya Nadella: Like, I— my general ledger better be a general ledger.
Satya Nadella: I don't need new schema creation.
Satya Nadella: Uh, in fact, that entity relationship, uh, is actually pretty good, robust thing that I want
Satya Nadella: to feed.
Sarah Guo: And you want it to be stable.
Satya Nadella: That's right. Yeah. Then, same thing with business logic, right?
Satya Nadella: If you look at— we have this product called Power BI, right?
Satya Nadella: It was like dashboards galore people created.
Satya Nadella: The beauty underneath that dashboard is a very rich semantic model, right?
Satya Nadella: Someone took the pain to create a dashboard and do all the measures.
Satya Nadella: And you want that— that's business logic, right?
Satya Nadella: I want that to be available to me.
Satya Nadella: So, I think that the challenge of the SaaS business model is we packaged one way.
Satya Nadella: We now have to learn how to unbundle these things and rebundle in new ways and discover new
Satya Nadella: business models, right?
Satya Nadella: I mean, if you look at it, what's happening today with Microsoft 365 is a great example.
Satya Nadella: Right? We have this thing called Work IQ.
Satya Nadella: In fact, like, what we are realizing is, oh my god, like, you know, if you look at— in fact,
Satya Nadella: there's a historical parallel to it, right?
Satya Nadella: We sold first Exchange and SharePoint and, uh, you know, before Teams, we had a thing called
Satya Nadella: Lync Server and what have you.
Satya Nadella: And we thought, "Oh, that's all going to move to the cloud."
Satya Nadella: But little did we realize that, oh, the number of people who will use servers in the cloud
Satya Nadella: is 10x, 100x, right, because people were not buying servers, they were just buying a subscription.
Satya Nadella: Mhm. The same thing is now happening with M365 because with Work IQ, we've exposed what is
Satya Nadella: perhaps the most important database in a company that never got used as a database because
Satya Nadella: it was only captive to our apps, right?
Satya Nadella: Mhm. It was, oh, email operated on it, Teams operated on it, Word, Excel, PowerPoint, SharePoint.
Satya Nadella: But now, like, this is one of the coolest things I get to do with Work IQ.
Satya Nadella: I go to a GitHub repo and I say, "Hey, I— I attended a bunch of design meetings last week
Satya Nadella: related to this repo. Can you capture all that and tell me what changes I should make?"
Satya Nadella: I mean, think about that.
Satya Nadella: Right? It literally can go look at all those transcripts, come back with a plan to change
Satya Nadella: your codebase. Right? Previously, you could have never thought of using M365 for something
Satya Nadella: like that. So, the value creation opportunity now in the agent world is, in fact, 10x more.
Satya Nadella: But it does require us to have, for example, there's going to be usage around M365, right,
Satya Nadella: which is going to be perhaps more than even the— the end users.
Satya Nadella: And we have to even re-architect, like, in fact, like, what I use to serve an inbox or a mailbox
Satya Nadella: cannot be used to serve an agent.
Satya Nadella: Uh, and so, that's sort of what we are doing.
Sarah Guo: I don't believe in like permanent business models for any of these domains, but— but in the
Sarah Guo: near term, do you have a prediction between, uh, you know, outcomes-based pricing, token-based
Sarah Guo: pricing, enterprise bundles?
Satya Nadella: Yeah, the way I think about this is always we had— let's even take the per-user pricing.
Satya Nadella: Mhm. The per-user pricing is really an artifact of someone creating a budget, needing certainty.
Satya Nadella: Right? Because it's the most important— like, somebody wants a budget, they need a per-user.
Satya Nadella: And— and per-user is just a set of entitlements to usage.
Satya Nadella: Right? That's kind of what it is.
Satya Nadella: And so, the way is, the first bundling will be, take some usage, bundle it into per-user stacks,
Satya Nadella: and, you know, then sell subscription.
Satya Nadella: So, subscriptions, I think, are going to be there, per-user is going to be there.
Satya Nadella: Then, the next big thing will be consumption.
Satya Nadella: So, people will say, "I want consumption."
Satya Nadella: And it's also possible that people will say, "I don't even want to pay for any of the subscriptions
Satya Nadella: or the consumption, it's outcome."
Satya Nadella: But remember, most people love outcomes until they have an outcome, because once you have
Satya Nadella: an outcome, it's like giving away royalty.
Satya Nadella: Right? I mean, like, I— I've talked to customers who love, you know, outcome-based pricing,
Satya Nadella: and I say, "I'm all in," until they, "Oh my god, like, what are you talking about?
Satya Nadella: You're sharing in my outcome?
Satya Nadella: No, no, no, I want you to go back to per-user pricing, and I want you to consumption price,"
Satya Nadella: right? So, I think that debate will go on.
Satya Nadella: Uh, but and all— all of these business models have a particular time and a place versus one
Satya Nadella: to rule them all. And if anything, if you're a SaaS vendor or you're a platform vendor, having
Satya Nadella: that flexibility— and quite frankly, we face this with GitHub, right?
Satya Nadella: We just recently announced a per-user pricing on GitHub.
Satya Nadella: Because little, you know, GitHub Copilot was constructed at a per-user level before we
Satya Nadella: understood even, uh, the intensity of usage of agents, right?
Satya Nadella: It was an interactive way for a developer to use code complete, maybe tasks.
Satya Nadella: It was not like, oh, I launch 10,000 sort of agents that are going on all day.
Satya Nadella: Right? So, that is what the adjustment is about.
Satya Nadella: So, now that we really want, there will always be a per-user, but there will have to be a
Satya Nadella: consumption meter.
Elad Gil: How do you think about the durability of SaaS more generally?
Elad Gil: One thing I've observed is in a lot of enterprises internally, there will be teams that almost
Elad Gil: have agent euphoria. They're so excited about the explosion of things they can build that
Elad Gil: they're trying to rebuild a lot of applications or going to their SaaS vendors and saying,
Elad Gil: "We're not going to work with you anymore, we're considering an internal project."
Elad Gil: And it seems like in six to nine months, maybe some of those people will come back and say,
Elad Gil: "Actually, we— we can't rebuild everything."
Elad Gil: How do you think about what's durable in this world and what isn't?
Satya Nadella: Yeah, it's a— I think we have to go through one full budget cycle on this to really see the
Satya Nadella: sort of the emergence of the equilibrium, because at the end of the day, there's marginal
Satya Nadella: cost to even generating the app, right?
Satya Nadella: In fact, there can be even a— a simple way to say it, like, you should always acquire something
Satya Nadella: if the marginal cost of building and maintaining, uh, something on your own is higher.
Satya Nadella: Uh, right? That should be like, it's a quantifiable—
Satya Nadella: Right, a quantifiable thing.
Satya Nadella: And the maintenance part is important, right?
Satya Nadella: Even like, you got to remember like, hey, you know, all the security stuff that now AI will
Satya Nadella: find, you better fix them too, fast.
Satya Nadella: Uh, of course, there's a coding agent to help you with, but then that burns tokens, (laughter)
Satya Nadella: right? So, who's responsibility is it?
Satya Nadella: It's kind of like a— a cycle that you got to think through.
Satya Nadella: And I think we have gone through the excitement that I can generate a lot of software.
Satya Nadella: I think the next thing would be, what software do I really want to generate?
Satya Nadella: What software do I want to use from others?
Satya Nadella: How do I compose these two into some agentic workflow that I have agency over?
Satya Nadella: Right? Because I think there will be very little tolerance for anybody who is inflexible,
Satya Nadella: uh, at the vendor level.
Satya Nadella: Uh, but at the same time, I think that anyone who has got that flexibility, shows up, delivers
Satya Nadella: the value, will be back at, again, right, with selling software, but with just different business
Satya Nadella: models, in fact.
Elad Gil: Uh, speaking about building software, um, one of my favorite moments from I think a previous
Elad Gil: Build, maybe one or two years ago, was they had a picture of you— there was a section of you
Elad Gil: building your own software.
Elad Gil: I'm curious if you're building anything now.
Satya Nadella: Yeah, so, I— I think the, you know, first of all, let's face it, right?
Satya Nadella: Building software has made it possible for even the incompetence of a CEO of a company like
Satya Nadella: ours (laughter) uh, you can build.
Satya Nadella: So, thank god. But that said, I— I— I— I do feel that, you know, something like,
Satya Nadella: um, GitHub Copilot to me, and especially the new sessions app or the new app, has just made
Satya Nadella: it so much more possible for you to have agency over artifacts that you felt you
Satya Nadella: couldn't touch before, right?
Satya Nadella: So, for me as a CEO, even, to go to a codebase, uh, to be able to learn about it.
Satya Nadella: Like, I remember joining Microsoft long back, you know, first, and then they said, "Well,
Satya Nadella: everybody had to go in and look at," you know, whatever, "Cutler's malloc or what have you
Satya Nadella: to learn how to do good C, uh, C++ code."
Satya Nadella: Um, so, now that ability to be more full-stack up and down is so good.
Satya Nadella: But that doesn't mean every one of us should be doing the same thing.
Satya Nadella: The question is, how do you then have the ability to inspect things, learn things, see things,
Satya Nadella: um, I think, is just so much more.
Satya Nadella: And so, to me, what I'm building a lot of is these long-running foundry agents.
Satya Nadella: Uh, right? So, there's autopilots.
Satya Nadella: So, the easiest thing is, to me, I think I just built one, uh, even last week where the idea
Satya Nadella: was, hey, can I have an agent that is continuously monitoring essentially my own
Satya Nadella: chief of staff autopilot, right?
Satya Nadella: We're going to have that obviously in Scout, that's what, uh, we showed.
Satya Nadella: But it was so easy and trivial to build.
Satya Nadella: I took Work IQ, I said, "Take Work IQ, go, uh, and build a foundry long-running agent, uh,
Satya Nadella: store all the memory in, um, uh, using Rayfin," right, basically, my backend as a service.
Satya Nadella: And lo and behold, it built it, and not only built it, I could say, "Publish to Teams," and
Satya Nadella: it published the damn thing to Teams.
Satya Nadella: So, the ability, uh, to have, you know, some end-to-end project like this complete is just
Satya Nadella: pretty miraculous.
Elad Gil: How do you think that impacts the different types of engineering roles that exist in the future?
Elad Gil: Because right now, I think there's, you know, a dozen different types of engineers you can
Elad Gil: be, from QA, front-end, etc.
Elad Gil: You know, there's a big swath.
Elad Gil: I've heard some people argue that in four or five years, we'll basically end up with four
Elad Gil: engineering roles. It'll be people who are managing agents, it'll be forward deployed engineers
Elad Gil: or FDEs, it'll be security engineers, and then people working on large-scale infrastructure
Elad Gil: for a small number of services, and then everything else just collapses into the agentic world.
Elad Gil: Do you think that's a correct view of the world?
Satya Nadella: Yeah, I mean, I think we'll have to experiment our way through it.
Satya Nadella: But what you said is what?
Satya Nadella: There are some very at-scale things.
Satya Nadella: At LinkedIn, they did structurally change, uh, and, you know, basically built up a new discipline
Satya Nadella: called full-stack builder, right?
Satya Nadella: So, they went and said, "Hey, let's bring, uh, people from design and product management,
Satya Nadella: front-end engineering, all pull them together."
Satya Nadella: Uh, but also have an edge, right?
Satya Nadella: It's not like the design person still doesn't have the design edge, or the front-end person
Satya Nadella: doesn't have the front-end edge.
Satya Nadella: But you can give yourself bigger scope in roles so that you're not confined to one role.
Satya Nadella: Um, and then, equally, infrastructure has become very critical, right?
Satya Nadella: So, in other words, like, I mean, our L&E, I mean, one thing we've realized is, even for the
Satya Nadella: Excel team, for example, building the RLE in which a reward can be learned is
Satya Nadella: actually one of the hardest sort of infrastructure problems.
Satya Nadella: Um, and so, you kind of need even new talent, right?
Satya Nadella: Distributed systems people even in what was considered an end-user app team, uh, because it's
Satya Nadella: a different skill set. So, yes, infrastructure, science is the other one, obviously.
Satya Nadella: Um, so, I think we'll see how these evolve, right?
Satya Nadella: Where's the real— I mean, always, the world will have a bunch of specialists.
Satya Nadella: Um, you know, I think the generalist role is going to be the most exciting,
Satya Nadella: right? Because the leverage of a generalist, um, is where we are going to see the maximum
Satya Nadella: returns, right? When you— when you'd said, "Hey, are you coding?"
Satya Nadella: I'm now a general— like, what— I've basically translated knowledge work, right, which I did,
Satya Nadella: where I created a Word document or a spreadsheet, or even, uh, and now I can build an app,
Satya Nadella: right? It's in— in the same sentence.
Satya Nadella: Um, right, that idea that, oh, wow, my generalist skills have gotten a higher leverage, I
Satya Nadella: think, is what we're going to see across the board.
Sarah Guo: Music to the ears of CEOs and VCs that are like, a little dangerous, and a lot of times—
Elad Gil: Golden age for idea people.
Sarah Guo: Idea people, man, with a lot of agency.
Sarah Guo: If you take that idea of personal agency and you just zoom it out to the organizational context,
Sarah Guo: um, uh, my partner, Mike Vernal, who, uh, actually started his career at Microsoft, just wrote
Sarah Guo: an essay where one of the big takeaways is, it's an age where you can be much more ambitious,
Sarah Guo: and you need to be, given the pace of the environment and how quickly actually users and companies
Sarah Guo: are open to adopting new technologies.
Sarah Guo: Um, how do you think about— I feel silly asking this of somebody running a, you know, trillion-dollar-plus
Sarah Guo: company already, but how do you think about how Microsoft can be more ambitious now?
Satya Nadella: It's a great question. Um, I think, um, I think the— the thing in these type of transitions
Satya Nadella: is to have a conceptual model of how
Satya Nadella: work can change to go after outcomes that you could hardly imagine
Satya Nadella: previously, right? In fact, Kevin Scott has this nice line, right, which is, um, "When you
Satya Nadella: can make the impossible—" like, "When you're making hard things easier, that's sort of one
Satya Nadella: point of leverage. But true ambition is about making the impossible possible."
Satya Nadella: So, now, the thing that is missing a little bit in all of our organizations is, what is that
Satya Nadella: new conceptual model of what can we build?
Satya Nadella: What was impossible, and what can we build?
Satya Nadella: And I'll give you one example of this, right, which is, I take great inspiration from sort
Satya Nadella: of the people who were managing the Azure network.
Satya Nadella: And they came to the— this was from even last year.
Satya Nadella: You know, we were scaling.
Satya Nadella: You saw that I— I talked about sort of how we built in the last 15 months more Azure capacity
Satya Nadella: than we built in the first 15 years.
Satya Nadella: I mean, it's crazy.
Satya Nadella: Right, it's pretty wild.
Satya Nadella: And it's the same team.
Satya Nadella: So, they saw that, and they said, "Wow, this just ain't going to work if we don't reconceptualize
Satya Nadella: our work." So, they built, essentially, they said, "Our job is not to do Azure networking.
Satya Nadella: Our job is to build the agentic system that does Azure networking," right?
Satya Nadella: These are the folks managing the 500-plus fiber operators managing the WAN, right,
Satya Nadella: all over. And fiber operations ultimately is a physical operation.
Satya Nadella: Things get cut, things get, you know, have to be repaired.
Satya Nadella: You know, we have fancy words called DevOps and so on.
Satya Nadella: Basically, emails are coming in, and you got to go respond to them, take care of it.
Satya Nadella: So, they built this agentic system.
Satya Nadella: They even have a character for it.
Satya Nadella: It's called Miles, and it sort of does all this stuff.
Satya Nadella: Right, they started sort of screaming for more tokens and so on.
Satya Nadella: And so, they were saying, "Look, we don't need headcount.
Satya Nadella: We need tokens in order to be able to manage, uh, our operation."
Satya Nadella: That reconceptualization of what their work is, right?
Satya Nadella: They— they basically took their work and made it meta, right?
Satya Nadella: That meta-work is now their new work.
Satya Nadella: Um, right? In the '80s, if somebody had come to us and said, "4 billion people are going to
Satya Nadella: get up in the morning and start typing," my model would have been, "We need 4 billion typists."
Satya Nadella: But we're not doing typing, we're doing knowledge work.
Satya Nadella: So, that to me, I think, is it, right, which is, whether it's Microsoft or whether it's any
Satya Nadella: organization, is to give ourselves permission to do new types of metacognition, meta-work,
Satya Nadella: using these new tools to change the outputs that matter, uh, and then really make the impossible
Satya Nadella: possible. So, completing that dot or the— the connective tissue across those, I think, is
Satya Nadella: where a lot of the enterprise value will get created.
Elad Gil: Should we talk about data centers?
Satya Nadella: Yeah, please ask.
Elad Gil: Oh, okay. Well, uh, this leads nicely into the data center buildup.
Elad Gil: I always think, uh, I'm just impressed with the sheer scale of the build out from Microsoft,
Elad Gil: but also everyone else, that this is redefining what it means to be a hyperscaler.
Elad Gil: And I just feel like that— that that has had unprecedented scale on finances, uh, on the way
Elad Gil: you run the company, but also the communities that are— that are impacted.
Elad Gil: Um, can you talk a bit more about what you're seeing on the ground, like when you visit your—
Satya Nadella: Yeah, I think there are two aspects of it.
Satya Nadella: Obviously, the build out is, uh, extraordinary.
Satya Nadella: Um, you know, nothing like this has happened, and it's great to be one of the participants
Satya Nadella: in it. Uh, but you brought up the other part, right?
Satya Nadella: I think at this point, it's clear that unless we as an industry, um, are
Satya Nadella: very principled about ensuring that the benefits of all the stuff we're talking about are
Satya Nadella: felt in real ways, uh, at the community level, right?
Satya Nadella: Because this is not just a— a campaign.
Satya Nadella: Um, right, it has to be real where people are saying, "Look, this is not changing the prices
Satya Nadella: on energy for me." In fact, if anything, it's bringing down prices because long-term, there's
Satya Nadella: going to be a better grid, there is going to be more energy.
Satya Nadella: Water consumption is, in fact, not sort of, uh, in fact, water is being replenished, right?
Satya Nadella: You got to really, you know, show, educate folks on truly what's happening, the— the closed-loop
Satya Nadella: systems we're building.
Satya Nadella: We have to invest in the training, the jobs, the tax base.
Satya Nadella: In fact, the least talked about stuff is the amount of jobs that get created during construction,
Satya Nadella: after construction, what's the tax base that's there in the community.
Satya Nadella: And— and all this has to be real.
Satya Nadella: Um, and— and if that is the case, then we will have permission.
Satya Nadella: If it is not, we won't have permission.
Satya Nadella: It's as simple as that, right?
Satya Nadella: Which is, uh, we— I think we have to take it as an industry pretty seriously.
Satya Nadella: Uh, I think it's good for communities to be skeptical, ask the hard questions, for us to do
Satya Nadella: the hard work, earn that.
Satya Nadella: Um, but at the end of the day, if this— if we can really be the— I've always felt like in
Satya Nadella: human history, if you use a lot of energy but also create a lot of value for society, the
Satya Nadella: story has been fantastic.
Satya Nadella: If you don't do that, it's not been that great.
Satya Nadella: And this time around, I'm a firm believer that ultimately, if you do have a token economy
Satya Nadella: that drives productivity, that drives economic growth, that drives broad-spread, um, you know,
Satya Nadella: participation, better health outcomes, um, then I think we will be in a great place.
Satya Nadella: Uh, and that's at least what we all have to be focused on.
Elad Gil: Yeah, it makes me think, actually, that with all these initiatives that you're doing, might
Elad Gil: be easier to see ROI in the communities first before in enterprise.
Satya Nadella: I mean, I think both sides.
Satya Nadella: In fact, it comes back together.
Satya Nadella: It has to be— the people in the communities are going to be employed, are going to be participants,
Satya Nadella: uh, in the real economy, right?
Satya Nadella: That's, I think, the question is.
Satya Nadella: Like, if we— if the broad economy is doing well, and the communities are doing well, the dots
Satya Nadella: get connected. It's sort of— the market forces are such that we will connect the dots.
Satya Nadella: And that, I think, is it.
Satya Nadella: Like, you got to be able to see the evidence.
Satya Nadella: It can't be about any one company, uh, but it has to be broad economic growth and broad, you
Satya Nadella: know, community permission.
Elad Gil: What are you most optimistic about currently, or what have you most updated your personal
Elad Gil: models on regarding society— societal impact of AI?
Satya Nadella: So, you're saying what's the— what have—
Elad Gil: What have you updated most on in terms of societal impact of AI?
Satya Nadella: Yeah, I think the— the most
Satya Nadella: critical thing is the first question we even started with, which is, we need to tell
Satya Nadella: the story and make it real that everybody has a real shot to
Satya Nadella: participate as a first-class participant in this new economy.
Satya Nadella: Right, that's kind of, I think, in the next 12 months, 18 months, we need a way for
Satya Nadella: people to say, "Oh, wow, I get it."
Satya Nadella: Right, there's going to be tremendous capability, tremendous amount of infrastructure.
Satya Nadella: But I can see what's going to happen, whether it's the benefits like health outcomes, or my
Satya Nadella: ability to create a startup, or my ability to run my local sort of, uh, store more
Satya Nadella: efficiently. It's just happening, and I see that, uh, benefit myself, right?
Satya Nadella: That to me, you know, earning that permission in a path-dependent way, we can't wait.
Satya Nadella: See, the one thing you'll have— I've now learned is, I think the world is going to be way
Satya Nadella: skeptical of tech and tech companies
Satya Nadella: that say, "Trust us. We've got it.
Satya Nadella: The future is going to be glorious."
Satya Nadella: Uh, you kind of have to deliver tangible benefits, um, and,
Satya Nadella: quite frankly, politicians winning elections, uh, because they've advocated for that.
Satya Nadella: That will be at least my adjustment, because without it, um, thinking that somehow— because
Satya Nadella: it is too important this time around.
Satya Nadella: It's too much of the economy for it not to be the case.
Sarah Guo: So, one very simple framework I have for
Sarah Guo: what is going to be the broad benefit of AI beyond the communities just working in technology,
Sarah Guo: uh, are sort of wealth creation, which is going to happen in a ton of different companies,
Sarah Guo: startups and large companies.
Sarah Guo: Then you have healthcare.
Sarah Guo: You— you had amazing demos today.
Sarah Guo: There are companies like OpenEvidence.
Sarah Guo: I think that is happening.
Sarah Guo: Um, education seems like another one that's an obvious good, where we haven't seen as much
Sarah Guo: impact as I'd expect. Do you have a hypothesis on why that might be, or if it'll come?
Satya Nadella: Yeah, I mean, I think this is where, again, how we think about education, how, you know, recently
Satya Nadella: I met with the founders of Alpha School and learned a lot about what they were going and going
Satya Nadella: about. And it's fascinating to listen, uh, to how to even rethink, uh, what does education
Satya Nadella: really look like. Because I think it's actually very important.
Satya Nadella: Uh, and I'm not saying anything traditionally being done is less important, right?
Satya Nadella: I was even looking at the— um, it's fascinating to see, I— I forget the which Stanford class
Satya Nadella: it was, uh, the— the Asian guidelines for CS something.
Satya Nadella: Um, (laughter) because you still need people to learn.
Satya Nadella: Uh, like, it was an interesting AI class that they were making sure people were learning how
Satya Nadella: to apply Softmax appropriately versus saying, "Hey, fix my training run."
Satya Nadella: Um, so, I think learning concepts is important.
Satya Nadella: It's going to be a critical— but the way we create the incentives, what are the credentials,
Satya Nadella: how we value those credentials, what is the employment opportunity for those credentials.
Satya Nadella: So, I think that there is a complete change that has to happen, uh, given the way to get to
Satya Nadella: information, way to educate yourself, way to continuously keep yourself updated has changed
Satya Nadella: so much. So, I think, interestingly enough, maybe the next big startup and success story could
Satya Nadella: be someone who builds a new university, um, or a new, um, pedagogy even of
Satya Nadella: how to get someone to go through a curriculum and find economic opportunity, uh, that's highly
Satya Nadella: valuable.
Sarah Guo: Well, that has felt, uh, perhaps impossible for a long time, but it's a great note to end
Sarah Guo: on and something that might be possible.
Sarah Guo: Thank you, Satya.
Satya Nadella: Thank you so much. Thank you.
Elad Gil: Thank you. I appreciate it.
Satya Nadella: Thank you all.